Next up we have dictionaries. These are the dictionaries are a data type that
allow us to store key and value pairs. Dictionaries themselves are mutable, but
just like sets dictionary keys can only be immutable. Why? Because dictionary
key is need to be hashable. Dictionaries allow fast item lookup and fast
membership testing. You can quickly say, given a key is this key in my dictionary or
not. And that's because the hash of the key is compared with the hash of the
keys in the dictionary. Don't have to look through each item in that
dictionary and say, are you the item? Are you the item? Are you the item that I'm
looking for? So can I have a list as a dictionary in a key? I'm sorry, a list
as a key in the dictionary. If I asked that question correctly, I would get a
better answer. No, right? So a list is mutable. Dictionary keys can only be
immutable. We cannot have mutable data types as dictionary keys. Can we have a
tuple as a dictionary key? Yes, tuples are immutable. So we can use them as
a dictionary key. I have a dictionary key key here for you, but let's go through
some examples of what dictionaries and Python look like. So if sets had curly
braces, dictionaries have curly braces and colons. And that colon is how you
differentiate between the key and the value. If I wanted to create an empty
dictionary, how do I do that? We already saw that.
Just two curly braces. If I wanted to create dictionaries with items in them, I
would now have to define keys and values. And separate them with commas. So the key
is on the left hand side of the colon. The value is on the right hand side of
the colon separated with commas. And that has now given me a dictionary with two
key value pairs in it. I can go ahead and assign this to a variable and then check
it's type. And that will show me that it is a dictionary. Now, dictionary keys
need to be immutable. Dictionary values do not have that same restriction. So you can
say my numbers are a dictionary and let's say the key is one and the value is this list.
That is totally fine. Because when I want to retrieve this item from my dictionary, I'll
be doing it by its key. Now, dictionaries like sets do not have an order in my
deck. There is no zero with item or first item. If I try to access the zero with item,
I'm going to get an error saying I expect a key and that key does not exist. So to
access items in a dictionary, you use the square bracket notation, but instead of providing
an index, like you would with a list or a tuple, you instead provide a key. And now that's
going to get the value from my dictionary that has the key of one. If I try to get a
value that doesn't exist, again, I get a key error. If I wanted to get something from
my dictionary and not deal with an exception that I then have to catch, I can use the
key to get item. Get method. And this will not throw an error if that key does not exist.
The get method has a second optional argument that is a default value. So I can say if this
key does not exist, return this default instead. If I pass in a key here that does exist,
what will I see? Will I see default? No, I'm going to get back the number two from my
deck because that key exists. Therefore, the default is not relevant. To add and remove items
from dictionaries, you can use that same notation that we used to update items in lists.
But instead of passing in a position, you're going to pass in a key. So if I wanted to update
the dictionary at key two, I could use this notation. And now my dict has but very silly
long string in it. I could use the same notation for adding items to the dictionary that
I don't already exist. And now I have a new key in there. Just like with sets, you could
update, you can call dot update on a dictionary and pass in another dictionary and that
will combine the two dictionaries together. So whatever dictionary you're calling dot
update on will be the one that is modified. You can have pretty complex dictionaries.
Remember a dictionary can have a list as a value. Let's say this key is one and the value
is a list. If I call my names and pass in this key of one, I'm going to get back a list.
I can call dot append on a list, which means that I can just chain these actions together.
So if I know that this returns a list, I can call dot append on it and append to this
list just like I normally would. Now if I look at my dictionary, oops, and I spell it correctly,
we'll see that I have appended a list to my list. So dictionaries can get very complex.
The values in them can be objects. So when you look at them, you might have to break down
which type is which in the value and be mindful of curly braces, parentheses, square brackets
to figure out what type is what. If you want to work with the values in a dictionary, there
are three methods that you need to know about. One is dot keys that will get you all of the keys.
One is dot values that will get you all of the values. But the most important one that you're
going to use most often is mydict.items. And that's going to return all of the key and value pairs.
When you're going to try to loop over a dictionary, you might expect that what is actually
returned is going to be the items, the key value pairs. But unfortunately, that is not correct.
When you loop over a dictionary, what's actually returned is just the keys. So something
to be mindful of. If you want to loop over a dictionary, which will look at later, you
want to make sure that you call dot items on it to get both the key and the value pairs.
So just a quick thing about mutability, the simple types in float decimal string, boolean,
tuple, those are immutable lists, sets, dictionaries are mutable. So if you don't remember,
take a look at the mutability cheat sheet. For the time being, we are going to skip over
the practice for this chapter and go through it with the next chapter.